Guide to the Pavel Nikolaevich Miliukov Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Pavel Nikolaevich Miliukov Papers,
ca. 1879-1970
Miliukov, P. N. (Pavel Nikolaevich), 1859-1943.
ca. 4,000 items (4 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. New York, NY.
4077838
Biographical Note
Historian, journalist, and leader of the Kadet (Constitutional Democratic) Party. Among Mili︠u︡kov's historical studies were "Russia and its Crisis" (1905) and "Ocherki po istorii russkoĭ kult́ury" (1930-37). He was delegate to the Russian State Duma and a member of the Provisional government in 1917. He edited "Rech"́ in St. Petersburg and "Posledniia Novosti" in Paris.
Scope and Content
There are letters from fellow historians, such as John Franklin Jameson and Aleksandr Lappo-Danilevskiĭ; Kadet Party leaders, including Vladimir D. Nabokov and Nikolaĭ Astrov; and others such as Boris Bakhmeteff, Charles Crane, Vladimir Jobotinsky, Louis Marshall, Thomas Masaryk, and Nikolaĭ Roerich. A large correspondence series consists of letters and petitions sent to Miliukov during the Third State Duma (1907-12). Manuscripts include Mili︠u︡kov's memoirs, and his notebooks from the period of the Civil War. There is also a manuscript by Isaak Shkovskiĭ (pseudonym -- Dioneo) on Russian writers and journalists during World War I. Subject files deal with the State Duma, the Civil War, and the emigration.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Cataloged Materials
Subseries I.1: Correspondence
Subseries I.2: Manuscripts
Subseris I.3: Documents
Series II: Arranged Materials
Subseries II.1: Correspondence
Subseries II.2: Manuscripts
Subseries II.3: Subject Files
Subseries II.4: Estate Files
Subseries II.5: Printed and Miscellaneous
Subjects
Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1894-1917.; Emigration and immigration--Soviet Union--20th century.; Emigration and immigration--Europe--20th century.; Journalism--Soviet Union.; Letters.; Memoirs.; Notebooks.; Petitions.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1954 Papers Heirs Gift
1956 Papers Purchase
1980 Papers Alexander Elkin Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Materials
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    - Adzhemov, Moisej Sergeevich (Box 1)
    - Alekseev, Mikhail Vasil'evich (Box 1)
    - Alvensleben, Werner von (Box 1)
    - Arsen'ev, Konstantin Konstantinovich (Box 1)
    - Astrov, Nikolai Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Avksent'ev, Nikolai Dmitrievich (Box 1)
    - Bakhmetev, Boris Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Bal'mont, Konstantin Dmitrievich (Box 1)
    - Batiushkov, Fedor Dmitrievich (Box 1)
    - Bobrov, Evgenii Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Bulgakov, Sergej Nikolaevich (Box 1)
    - Bourdillon, Bernard Henry (Box 1)
    - Burtsev, Vladimir L'vovich (Box 1)
    - Chelnokov, Mikhail Vasil'evich (Box 1)
    - Chirikov, Evgenii Nikolaevich (Box 1)
    - Crane, Charles R. (Box 1)
    - Croft, Henry Page (Box 1)
    - Davydova, Aleksandra Arkad'evna (Box 1)
    - Debogorii-Mokrievich, Vladimir Karpovich (Box 1)
      [pseudonym - Kablukov P.]
    - Demidov, Igor' Platonovich (Box 1)
    - Denikin, Anton Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Dolgorukov, Pavel Dmitrievich (Box 1)
    - Dolgorukov, Petr Dmitrievich (Box 1)
    - Dzhivegelov, Aleksei Karpovich (Box 1)
    - Dzhunkovskii, E.P. (Box 1)
    - Efimovskii, Evgenii Amvrosievich (Box 1)
    - Efremov, Ivan Nikolaevich (Box 1)
    - El'kin, Boris Isaakovich (Box 1)
    - Evreinov, Boris Alekseevich (Box 1)
    - Famintsyn, Andrei Sergeevich (Box 1)
    - Fondaminskii, Il'ia Isidorovich (Box 1)
      [pseudonym - I.I. Bunakov]
    - Ganfman, Maksim Ippolitovich (Box 1)
    - Geiden, Petr Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Gershenzon, Mikhail Osipovich (Box 1)
    - Gessen, Iosif Vladimirovich (Box 1)
    - Golder, Frank Alfred (Box 1)
    - Gorbunov-Posadov, Ivan Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Gruzenberg, Oskar Osipovich (Box 1)
    - Guchkov, Aleksandr Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Izgoev, Aleksandr Solomonovich (Box 1)
      [pseudonym of A.S. Lande]
    - Iuzhakov, Sergei Nikolaevich (Box 1)
    - Iziumov, A.F. (Box 1)
    - Jabotinsky, Vladimir (Box 1)
    - Jameson, John Flanklin (Box 1)
    - Kartashev, Anton Vladimirovich (Box 1)
    - Kazem-Bek, Aleksandr L'vovich (Box 1)
    - Kharlamov, Vasilii Akomovich (Box 1)
    - Kizevetter, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Kizevetter, Ekaterina Iakovlevna (Box 1)
    - Kokoshkin, Fedor Fedorovich (Box 1)
    - Kondakov, Nikodim Pavlovich (Box 1)
    - Konovalov, Aleksandr Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Konovalov, Sergei Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Korf, Sergei Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Kornilov, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
    - Kornilov, Lavr Georgievich (Box 1)
    - Kovarskii, Il'ia Nikolaevich (Box 1)
    - Krym, Solomon Solomonovich (Box 1)
    - Kuprin, Aleksandr Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Kuskova, Ekaterina Dmitrievna (Mrs. S.N. Prokopovich) (Box 1)
    - Lamanskii, Vladimir Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Lappo-Danilevskii, Aleksandr Sergeevich (Box 1)
    - Leverkuhn, Paul (Box 1)
    - Levitskii, Aleksandr Aaronovich (Box 1)
    - Liubavskii, Matvei Kuz'mich (Box 1)
    - Losskii, Nikolai Onufrievich (Box 1)
    - Malchenko, Vasilii Stepanovich (Box 1)
    - Manteuffel, Tadeusz (Box 1)
    - Marshall, Louis (Box 1)
    - Masaryk, Thomas Garrigue (Box 1)
    - Maude, Aylmer (Box 1)
    - Mazon, Andre (Box 1)
    - Meisler, Dmitrii Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Miakotin, Venedikt Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
      ["see also: Box 5, Personal Correspondence, Folder VII: ""Soiuz vzaimopomoshchi russkikh pisatelei"" "]
    - Mikhailovskii, Nikolai Konstantinovich (Box 1)
    - Miliukov, Pavel Nikolaevich (Box 1)
    - Miliukova, Anna Sergeevna (Box 1)
    - Miller, Evgenii Karlovich (Box 1)
    - Miller, Vsevolod Fedorovich (Box 1)
    - Minorskii, Vladimir Fedorovich (Box 1)
    - Munshtein, Leonid Grigor'evich (Box 1)
      [pseudonym - Lolo]
    - Nabokov, Vladimir Dmitrievich (Box 2)
    - Obolenskii, Vladimir Andreevich (Box 2)
    - Ol'denburg, Sergei Sergeevich (Box 2)
    - Orlova, Elizaveta Nikolaevna (Box 2)
    - Osorgin, Mikhail (Box 2)
      [pseudonym of M.A. Il'in]
    - Paleologue, Maurice (Box 2)
    - Panina, Sofiia Vladimirovna (Box 2)
    - Panteleev, Longin Fedorovich (Box 2)
    - Pares, Bernard, sir (Box 2)
    - Parsons, Herbert (Box 2)
    - Phillips, John S. (Box 2)
    - Pogodin, Aleksandr L'vovich (Box 2)
    - Pokrovskii, Nikolai Vasil'evich (Box 2)
    - Portugalov, Viktor Veniaminovich (Box 2)
    - Radziszewski, Henryk (Box 2)
    - Reynolds, James Bronson (Box 2)
    - Rizov, D. (Box 2)
    - Roerich, Nikolai Konstantinovich (Box 2)
    - Root, Elihu (Box 2)
    - Rose, John Holland (Box 2)
    - Rostovtsev, Mikhail Ivanovich (Box 2)
    - Sadler, Michael Ernest (Box 2)
    - Savinkov, Boris Viktorovich (Box 2)
    - Schiff, Jacob H. (Box 2)
    - Semevskii, Vasilii Ivanovich (Box 2)
    - Shchepkin, Nikolai Nikolaevich (Box 2)
    - Shestov, Lev (Box 2)
    - Shishmanov, Ivan (Box 2)
    - Shklovskii, Isaak Vladimirovich (Box 2)
      [pseudonym - Dioneo]
    - Shtein, Sergei Vladimirovich (Box 2)
    - Slavik, Jan (Box 2)
    - Spargo, John (Box 2)
    - Speranskii, Nikolai Vasil'evich (Box 2)
    - Stead, William Thomas (Box 2)
    - Stepanov, Vasilii Aleksandrovich (Box 2)
    - Storozhev, Vasilii Nikolaevich (Box 2)
    - Straus, Oscar S. (Box 2)
    - Struve, Gleb Petrovich (Box 2)
    - Struve, Petr Berngardovich (Box 2)
    - Svatikov, Sergei Grigor'evich (Box 2)
    - Syromiatnikov, Boris Ivanovich (Box 2)
    - Tarle, Evgenii Viktorovich (Box 2)
    - Trubetskoi, Sergei Nikolaevich (Box 2)
    - Tyrkova-Williams, Ariadna Vladimirovna (Box 2)
    - Uspenskii, Fedor Ivanovich (Box 2)
    - Ustrialov, Nikolai Vasil'evich (Box 2)
    - Vasilenko, Nikolai Porfir'evich (Box 2)
    - Veselovskii, Iurii Alekseevich (Box 2)
    - Vinaver, Evgenii Maksimovich (Box 2)
    - Vinaver, Roza Georgievna (Box 2)
    - Vodovozov, Vasilii Vasil'evich (Box 2)
    - Zeeler, Vladimir Feofilovich (Box 2)
    - Zernov, Mikhail Sergeevich (Box 2)
    - Zvolianskii, Sergei Erastovich (Box 2)
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscripts
    - Aleksinskii, Grigorii Alekseevich List of Archival Materials (Box 2)
    - Bal'mont, Konstantin Dmitrievich Moskva; Prazdnik Licin; Kentavr; Pesnia o ptitsakh (Box 2)
      [poems]
    - Evreinov, Boris Alekseevich "Edinenie" - vol'naia tribuna molodezhi (Box 2)
      [essay]
    - Kerenskii, Aleksandr Fedorovich Ot vosstaniia 3 iiulia k generalu Kornilovu, ( ) (Box 2)
    - Savinkov Pro Memoria; Vozzvanie (Box 2)
      [microfilmed]
    - Shkovskii, Isaak Vladimirovich Russkie pisateli I zhurnalisty v 1914-1917 gg. (Box 2)
    - Struve, Petr Berngardovich Smysl proisshedshego na iuge Rosii (Box 2)
    - Teslenko, Nikolai Vasil'evich Pamiati zamuchennykh pravednikov (Box 2)
    - Ustrialov, Nikolai Vasil'evich Sdvigi P.N. Miliukova (Box 2)
  - Subseries I.3: Documents
    - Chkheidze, Nikolai Semenovich Receipt (Box 2)
    - Miliukov, Pavel Nikolaevich Membership card of the "Soiuz vzaimopomoshchi Russkikh Pisatelei" (Box 2)
      [signed by Petr Nikolaevich Isakov]
- Series II: Arranged Materials
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence
    - Sub-subseris II.1.1: Petitions - Appeals - Complaints (re: State Duma)
      In a chronologycal order
      - No date (Box 3, Folder I - VII)
      - 1900-1907 (Box 3, Folder VIII)
      - 1908 (Box 3, Folder IX-XIV)
      - 1909 (Box 4, Folder I-VI)
      - 1910 (Box 4, Folder VII-X)
      - 1911 (Box 4, Folder XI-XIII)
      - 1912 (Box 4, Folder XIV)
    - Sub-subseris II.1.2: Letters to P.N. Miliukov as an aditor of "Rech'" (1908-1912)
      In an alphabetical order
      - Anonymous and Unidentified (Box 5, Folder I)
      - Ber[?]ovskii, Aleksandr; Cherep-Spiridovich, A.; Feofilov, Ivan Andreevich; Gorelik, P.; Grishchenko, Il'ia Fomich; Iakubovich, P. (see: Morozov, N.A.); Kuchurin, M.F.; Kuznetsov, Nikolai Fedorovich; Mandel'shtam, I.; Mel'der, Martsiana Iosifovna; Militsyn, Nikolai Alekseevich; Morozov, Nikolai Aleksandrovich; Muskatblit, F.; Nal'di, R.; Opochinin, V.; Panov, A.; Panov, T.; Pekarskii, V.; Rakhmanov, Georgii Karpovich; Romm; Samokhvalov, Fedor Ivanovich; Seferg, Fedor; Senin, Aleksandr Ivanovich; Shavarskii, Mikhail Pavlovich; Shcherbak, Anton; Suits, Gustav; Tuzhilov, Aleksandr Petrovich; Vedrebiseli, D. (Dar'ia Konstantinovna Kal'gina-Malieva); Zagorodnii, N. (Box 5, Folder I)
    - Sub-subseris II.1.3: Personal Correspondence
      - Anonymous and Unidentified (Box 5, Folder II)
      - Academiia Nauk (Box 5, Folder III)
        ["see: Dubrovin, Nikolai Fedorovich"]
      - Brun, Mikhail Isaakovich; Davydov, Iosif Aleksandrovich; Dubrovin, Nikolai Fedorovich; Feofanov, Mikhail; Gebel', Valerian; Grunau, Artur Avgustovich (Box 5, Folder III)
      - Ianovskii; Ivanovskii, V.; Kachorovskii, Karl Romanovich (Box 5, Folder IV)
      - Komitet slavianskoi vzaimnosti (Box 5, Folder IV)
      - Korvin-Krukovskii, Nikolai Sergeevich (aka: N. Severnyi); Krasnopol'skaia M., Kuliabko-Koretskaia, A. Sa[?]; Kynchov, Vasil'; Levi, Nikolai Nikolaevich (Box 5, Folder IV)
      - Marsden, V.E.; Mlinarich, Ivan Petrovich; Nelidova, E.; Ogloblin, Nikolai Nikolaevich (Box 5, Folder V)
      - Paque, Desire; Prokhodtsov, Ivan Ivanovich; Reid, Mary W.; Rodicheva, E.; Rostovtsev, Dmitrii (Box 5, Folder VI)
      - Salazkin, Sergei Sergeevich; Selivanov, Aleksei Vasil'evich; Semenov, IU.; Sharapov, Sergei Fedorovich; Slonim, Moisei Il'ich (Box 5, Folder VII)
      - Soiuz vzaimopomoshchi russkikh pisatelei (Box 5, Folder VII)
        ["see also: Box 2, Cataloged Documents, Miliukov, Pavel Nikolaevich. Membership card "]
      - Sokolov, Vladimir Dmitrievich (Box 5, Folder VII)
      - Stakhovich, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich (Box 5, Folder VII)
      - Studencheskoe Istoricheskoe Obschestvo (Box 5, Folder VII)
      - Subotich [Subotin ?], D. (Box 5, Folder VII)
      - Trachevskaia, IU.; Vinogradov; Vinogradova, Mariia Konstantinovna (Box 5, Folder VIII)
      - Zlochevskii, Petr (Box 5, Folder VIII)
        [re: Feiga Kaplan]
    - Sub-subseris II.1.4: Correspondence 1918 -
      - Anonymous and Unidentified (Box 6, Folder I)
        [see also: Box 6, Folder XI - "Vserossiiskii Krestianskii Soiuz": Various Materials related to VKS]
      - Akatsatov, Mikhail Epifanovich (Box 6, Folder II)
        [see: Box 6, Folder XI - "Vserossiiskii Krestianskii Soiuz"]
      - Alekseev, Gregory; Alekseeva, A.; Allen, W.E.D.; Andreeva, I. (Box 6, Folder II)
      - American Relief Administration European Children's Fund (Box 6, Folder II)
      - Arkhipov, Vsevolod; Bagaturiants, Armenak Romanovich; Baikov, Mikhail; Barybin, T.; Belaia, D.; Berestov, P.; Berthelot; Blank, D.; Borisov, N. (Box 6, Folder II)
      - Braikevich, M.V. (Box 6, Folder II)
        [see: Box 6, Folder II: Bagaturiants, A.R.]
      - Bronshtein, Aleksandr Oskarovich; Brook, S. (Box 6, Folder II)
      - Chamanskii; Chirikova, Liudmila; Darowski; Demarquet, P.; D'iakonova, L.; Dmitrievskii, S.; Eisenmann, Louis; El'kin, Aleksandr Isaakovich; Emel'ianov, Ivan Vasil'evich (Box 6, Folder III)
      - Erdman, A. (Box 6, Folder III)
        [see: Box 6, Folder XI - ""Vserossiiskii Krestianskii Soiuz"": Various Materials related to VKS]
      - Evelinov, Boris E. (Box 6, Folder III)
      - Federation Internationale des Ligues pour la Defense des Droits de l'Homme et du Citoyen (Box 6, Folder III)
      - Fel'dman, R.; Fleet, Jina; Frangulis, A.; Fumanova, Zhenni (Box 6, Folder III)
      - Gay, G.I. (Box 6, Folder IV)
        [see: Box 6, Folder II: American Relief Administration European Children's Fund ]
      - Germanov, Nikolai (Box 6, Folder IV)
      - Gimn. O-vo Russkii Sokol " Praga I." v Prage (Box 6, Folder IV)
      - Gleises, Pierre envelopes (Box 6, Folder IV)
      - Gor[illegible]lov, M.; Greben[illegible], D.; Guermanoff, L. (Germanov); Gurovich, A. (Box 6, Folder IV)
      - Isaev, V.I. (Box 6, Folder IV)
        [see: Box 6, Folder IX - "Soiuz Russkikh Akademicheskikh organiztsii za granitsei"]
      - Ivanov, Joann K.; Ivanov, S.F.; Ivashkevich, D. (Box 6, Folder IV)
      - Kashkarov, P.I. (Box 6, Folder V)
        [letter also signed by Kolokol'tsov, Narozhonskii, Selichev, and Suchkov]
      - Kazak (Box 6, Folder V)
      - Kievskoe i Odesskoe soveshchanie chlenov byvshikh zakonodatel'nykh palat (Box 6, Folder V)
      - Kogan, Maksim Isaevich and B. (Box 6, Folder V)
        [see: Box 1, Cataloged Correspondence, Folder "Miliukova, Anna Sergeevna"]
      - Kolokol'tsov, N.V. (Box 6, Folder V)
        [letter also signed by Kashkorov, Narozhonskii, Selichev, and Suchkov]
      - Kolyshev, Petr Vladimirovich; Kolyshko, Ivan; Korostovets, Ara; Korostovets, Vladimir; Korssakkoff, Nicolas de (Box 6, Folder V)
      - Krasnov, V. (Box 6, Folder V)
        [see: Box 1, Cataloged Corr., Folder "Iziumov, A.F." and Box 2, Cataloged Corr., Folder "Slavik, Jan"]
      - Kravtsov, N.A.; Krofka, D.A.; Kruglov, V.; Kul'chitskaia, Mariia (Box 6, Folder V)
      - Laskin, N.; Lebedev, Vasilii Ivanovich; Lednitskii, V.; Leonidova, Ol'ga; Litvak, L. (Box 6, Folder VI)
      - Makletsov, Aleksandr Vasil'evich; Maliutin, Boris Evgen'evich; Maliutina, A.; Mandel'shtam, A.[?]; Manukhina, Tat'iana; Margolin, Arnol'd Davidovich; Margulis; Masalov, P.; Mellud[illegible]; Miliukov, Nikolai Pavlovich (Box 6, Folder VII)
      - Ministere des Affaires Etrangeres (Box 6, Folder VII)
        [see: Box 6, Folder II: Berthelot]
      - Mironov, M.P. (Box 6, Folder VII)
      - Mogilev[illegible] (Box 6, Folder VII)
        [see: Box 6, Folder VIII - "Posledniia Novosti"]
      - Mogilianskii (Box 6, Folder VII)
      - Narozhonitskii, I.P. (Box 6, Folder VIII)
        [see: Box 6, Folder V; letter also signed by Kashkorov, Kolokol'tsov, Selichev, and Suchkov]
      - Nemanov, L.M. (Box 6, Folder VIII)
        [see: Box 6, Folder XI "Vserossiiskii Krest'ianskii Soiuz"]
      - Nilus, Evgenii Khrisanfovich; Novitskii, Georgii (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Novoe Russkoe Slovo (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Nozdman, M. (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Onu, Aleksandr (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Oshanin, Nikolai Ivanovich; Osiatinskaia; Pagol; Papin; Patrizi, E.; Pavlovskii, A.D.; Petrov, I.A.; Petrushevich, I.; Pletnev, V. (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Poliakov, Nikolai Mikhailovich (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Polonskii, Iak. (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Posledniia Novosti (Box 6, Folder VIII)
      - Pechtsamer, Simon; Regendanz, W.G. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Revue de Geneve (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Roma[illegible], Al. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Rossiiskaia Voenno-Respublikanskaia Liga (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Rostovtsev, O. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Russkii Zagranichnyi Istoricheskii Arkhiv (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Rygalov, N.M.; Sachol, E. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Sack, A.J. (Box 6, Folder IX)
        [see: Zak, A.]
      - Safonova, M.; Sakhanov; Saposnekov, Jacob (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Selichev (Box 6, Folder IX)
        [see: Box 6, Folder V; letter also signed by Kashkorov, Kolokol'tsov, Narozhonskii, and Suchkov]
      - Semenov, P.; Shishkov, I.; Shoikevich, M.; Shumskii, K.; Sidorin, V. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Sitinskii, Leopol'd E. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Soiuz russkikh akademicheskikh organizatsii za granitsei (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Soiuz russkikh literatorov i zhurnalistov v Parizhe (Box 6, Folder IX)
        [see: Box 6, Folder VII - Mironov, M.P.]
      - Solov'eva, V.; Sorine; Strunski; Struve, N.A. (Box 6, Folder IX)
      - Stupnitskii, A.F. (Box 6, Folder IX)
        [see: Box 6, Folder V - Kolyshko, Ivan]
      - Suchkov, A.A. (Box 6, Folder IX)
        [see: Box 6, Folder V; letter also signed by Kashkorov, Kolokol'tsov, Narozhonskii, and Selichev]
      - Tanedel'man, Mariia; Thouvenet, H.; Tishchenko, Vera Iur'evna; Tiurnikova, Ekaterina; Tobolka, Jiri (Box 6, Folder X)
      - Union des Artisan Russes; Union des Techniciens de la Radio; University of London (Box 6, Folder X)
      - Uzunov, I.; Vasetskii, V.; Vesten; Vilenkin, Aleksandr (Box 6, Folder X)
      - Vilkov, Al. (Box 6, Folder X)
        [see: Box 6, Folder IX - "Soiuz Russkikh Akademicheskikh organizatsii za granitsei"]
      - Vinner, N. (Box 6, Folder X)
      - Vserossiiskii Krest'ianskii Soiuz (Box 6, Folder XI)
      - Weiner, N. (Box 6, Folder XII)
      - Westminster Bank Limited (Box 6, Folder XII)
      - Yarkoni, M.; Yate, A.C.; Zak, A. (Box 6, Folder XII)
  - Subseries II.2: Manuscripts
    - Sub-subseris II.2.1: Miliukov's Manuscripts
      - Memoirs: Photocopy; Original, parts I-IV (Box 7)
      - Memoirs: Original, parts V-end; Typed copy (incomplete) (Box 8)
      - Diaries and Notebooks (Box 9)
      - Transcription of "Diary", 1918-21 (transcription of selected diaries and notebooks done in 1950s) (Box 10)
      - Ocherki po istorii russkoi kul'tury (Box 11)
        [exerpts, fragments, notes]
      - Brief Autobiography; Desiatiletie russkoi revoliutsii; Rossiia na perelome (excerpts); Memoir of trips to Berlin, 1930; On the 19th Century Revolutionary Movement; Pervoe Vremennoe pravitel'stvo; Sotsiologicheskie osnovy russkogo istoricheskogo proesessa; Slavianskii vopros posle voiny; Brief Manuscripts (Box 12)
      - Lectures; Manuscript fragments and notes; Notes for Granat Encyclopedia's Biography of S.Iu. Witte; Notes on various undated meetings (Box 13)
    - Sub-subseris II.2.2: Manuscripts by Others
      - Bezobrazov, Aleksandr Mikhailovich "Izvlechenie iz moego doklada, predstavlennogo Gosudariu posle (pervoi) poezdki v Port-Artur", 1908 (Box 14, Folder I)
      - Communist Party Reports, 1921 (Box 14, Folder II)
      - Nepomeshchennye v "Poslednikh Novostiakh", 1922-1923 (Box 14, Folder III-IV)
      - "Otchet o deiatel'nosti ispolnitel'noi komissii soveshchaniia Vs. Uchreditel'nogo Sobraniia", 1921 (Box 14, Folder V)
      - Reports about Soviet Russia, ca. 1921-1922 (Box 14, Folder VI)
        [Unidentified sources]
    - Sub-subseris II.2.3: Manuscripts by Others - Brief Manuscripts
      In alphabetical order by authors
      - Akatsatov, Mikhail Epifanovich Article and Interview with P. Khalippa (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Baikalov, A. "O russko-ukrainskom soglashenii", 1932 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Bar[illegible], Aleksandr Anatol'evich, 1932 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Bassanovich, I.Iu. "O litovskikh narodnykh pesniakh" (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Berkenheim, Aleksandr "The Economic Blockade of Russia. Memorandum" (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Iakovlev, M. (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Iakovlev "Zagovor" Minskago GPU protiv sovetskoi vlasti (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Kiselev-Shumilov, Aleksandr Nikiforovich Zagrobnyi skitalets.Poema (kitaiskaia), 1908 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Kopf, Aleksandr Avgustovich "Predislovie k sochineniiu Arkheologicheskiia, istoricheskiia, pis'mennyia izsledovaniia pervobytnykh vremen Iuzhnoi Rusi", 1889 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Kre[?]venkov, T. (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Mogilianskii "K ukrainskomu voprosu" (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Pavlov, A.N. 1933 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Prazhanin "Chetvertyi Internatsional", 1932 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Soboleva, Elena "Nashi Chubarovtsy za granitsei" (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Stavrogin, A. "Pravda o savinkovtsakh", 1922 (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Vasil'ev, I. "Povtorenie krupnoi oshibki shestidesiatykh godov po nadeleniiu krest'ianskikh zemel'" (Box 14, Folder VII)
      - Zhitetskoi, I. "Verkhovnyi Tainyi Kabinet" (Box 14, Folder VII)
    - Sub-subseris II.2.4: Manuscripts by Others - Memoirs about Civil War
      - Korostovets, V.K. "Moia komandirovka iz Kieva v Iassy v 1918 godu" (Box 14, Folder VIII)
      - Litvin, Nikolai "Vrangeliada", Stambul (Box 14, Folder VIII)
      - Morozov, K. "Russkaia pechal'. (Iz dorozhnago dnevnika)", 1919 (Box 14, Folder VIII)
      - Tandefel't "Na shesti frontakh protiv bol'shevikov. Otryvki iz lichnykh vospominanii" (Box 14, Folder VIII)
      - Tillin[illegible] "XVII Armeiskii Korpus pered vystupleniem bol'shevikov i v dni bol'shevitskago perevorota" (Box 14, Folder VIII)
      - Vendziagol'skii, K. "Prebyvanie v Gatchine 28, 29, 30 i 31 oktiabria 1917 g. i posleduiushchie popytki bor'by s bol'shevikami do 16-18 noiabria t/g.", 1918 (Box 14, Folder VIII)
    - Sub-subseris II.2.5: Manuscripts by Others - Unidentified Authors
      In alphabetical order by title
      - Without Title; Aleksandr Dmitrievich Khomutov. Polkovnik Gvardii Izmailvoskago polka (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Analiz (Programma) by A.Z., 1879 (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Dettee Etrangere du gouvernement Sovietique, March, 1931 (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Dvizhenie Anarkh[istov] v Ros.[sii]; Istoriia Alekseevskoi armii; Izsledovanie mogil'nika; K russkomu obshchestvu (po povodu krovavago naveta na evreev); K volneniiam v Kurdinstane; Kogo dolzhna sudit' Frantsiia; Mozhet li Miliukov byt' gostem Latvii; O dukhobortsakh v Kanade; Outlook in Russia. Interview with Professor Milyukoff; Poslanie Pavlu Makedonskomu ot cheloveka, opozdavshego rodit'sia; Pozitsiia Germanii na konferentsii po razoruzheniiu (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Privet G-nu Rodichevu 3-ei Gosudarstvennoi Dumy po povodu intsidenta 17go Noiabria, 1907 (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Rathenau et la France (En commemoration de son assassinat le 24 Juin 1932); Rimskiiam kolonat (le Colonat romain); Rossiia i Turtsiia (Po povodu priezda g-na Miliukova) (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Russie et la situation politique d'apres guerre, Rome, 1918 (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Russie et les interest vitaux des allies, Rome, 1918 (Box 14, Folder IX)
      - Svedeniia o Tambovskom krest'ianskom vozstanii 1920-1921 gg.; Zapiski krasnago (Box 14, Folder IX)
  - Subseries II.3: Subject Files
    - Civil War (Box 15)
    - Duma (Box 15)